<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cloudengineeringacademy on mmb198 blog site</title>
    <link>https://mmb198.github.io/en/tags/cloudengineeringacademy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in cloudengineeringacademy on mmb198 blog site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-au</language>
    <copyright>mmb198</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 19:47:57 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mmb198.github.io/en/tags/cloudengineeringacademy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Engineer Academy Module 4 Blog - Linux and Bash chmod</title>
      <link>https://mmb198.github.io/en/posts/ca_module4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 19:47:57 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mmb198.github.io/en/posts/ca_module4/</guid>
      <description>chmod numeric chmod (change mode) is a command in Linux and other Unix-like operating systems that allows you to change the permissions (read, write, execute) of files and directories.&#xA;In Linux, permissions are represented by three sets of characters: user (owner), group, and others. Each set consists of three characters representing the read (r), write (w), and execute (x) permissions. These permissions can be represented numerically as well, where read=4, write=2, and execute=1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Engineer Academy Module 3 Blog - System Design and Architecture</title>
      <link>https://mmb198.github.io/en/posts/ca_module3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 21:32:09 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mmb198.github.io/en/posts/ca_module3/</guid>
      <description>The Cyber Engineering Academy started as a 12 week course with a new subject per week (12 weeks = 12 subjects) but this was a little ambitious! The reality is that a single week for AWS (week 5), isn&amp;rsquo;t enough time so this timeline has been blown out. I&amp;rsquo;ll now be referring to modules rather than weeks.&#xA;Module 3 - System Design and Architecture This module covered common architecture types (monolithic, microservices and serverless), Application Programmable Interfaces (APIs), Load Balancers and cloud storage options (object, block and file).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Engineer Academy Module 2 Blog - Git &amp; Cloud Architecture</title>
      <link>https://mmb198.github.io/en/posts/ca_week2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 21:37:43 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mmb198.github.io/en/posts/ca_week2/</guid>
      <description>Version Control Learnt about 3 main types of version control systems: 1. Local: All repositories/data are only held and accessible from a local machine, making it difficult to collaborate with others. 2. Centralised: The repository is kept on a main server, any updates have to be committed to the central server. 3. Distributed: Repositories are distributed across end users and servers. Any of the users or servers can act as the central repository.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Engineer Academy Module 1 Blog - Cloud Fundamentals</title>
      <link>https://mmb198.github.io/en/posts/ca_week1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2024 21:25:43 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mmb198.github.io/en/posts/ca_week1/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve embarked on a 12 week Cloud Engineering Academy, with the aim to increase my knowledge and skills in cloud computing. This is my first blog and I will be using this blog space to post summaries of my weekly study. The blog is currently hosted on Github and I am aiming to move the blog onto my cloud host as I progress through the course.&#xA;Week 1&#xA;To make my weekly summary, I start by making a list of topics/subjects that I study this week from my Obisidian note titles.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
